A Guide to the Harold H. Loucks Papers FA050
Rockefeller Archive Center
Harold H. Loucks papers
1920-1976, bulk 1951-1965
1951-1965
Rockefeller Archive Center
Loucks, Harold H.
China Medical Board (U.S)
Peking Union Medical College
Rockefeller Foundation. China Medical Board
FA050
1.14 Cubic Feet 3 document cases
Conditions Governing Access
Open for research. Brittle or damaged items are available at the discretion of RAC. Researchers interested in accessing digital media (floppy disks, CDs, DVDs, etc.) or audiovisual material (audio cassettes, VHS, etc.) in this collection must use an access surrogate. The original items may not be accessed because of preservation concerns. To request an access surrogate be made, or if you are unsure if there is an access surrogate, please contact an archivist.
Biographical / Historical
Harold Loucks was born in 1894, and graduated with an M.D. from Western Reserve University. In 1922 he became an assistant resident in Surgery at the Peking Union Medical College, and in 1930 he became the head of the Surgery department there. While at the PUMC he married Mary Swisher, the nurse-anesthetist for the college. Mr. Loucks was an employee of the China Medical Board from 1948 through 1955, and the China Medical Board of New York 1955-1963, 1965.
Scope and Contents
The papers focus on the years after World War II and the reconstruction of the Peking Union Medical College, and include reports and correspondence by Loucks from China Medical Board, Inc. sponsored trips to the Far East, 1951-1964. The countries surveyed include: Japan, Hong Kong, Philippines, Indonesia, Malaysia, Siam (Thailand), Burma, Ceylon, India, Pakistan, Lebanon, Korea, Vietnam, and the Trust Territory. The reports include information not only about the status of medical education, but also about the social and political climate of each country.
Arrangement
The Harold H. Loucks collection is divided into three series:
Series 1 - Correspondence Series 2 - China Medical Board, Inc. Series 3 - China Medical Board - Peking Union Medical College
File Plan
Former Classification: IV 2A 32
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Harold H. Loucks gave his papers to the Rockefeller Archive Center in 1979.
Indonesia; Political science; Philippines; Hong Kong; Japan; Ceylon; Burma; Thailand; Malaysia; Pakistan; Lebanon; Korea; China; Social history; Medical education; East Asia; Vietnam; India
- Correspondence, 1920-1976, bulk 1950-1976; 1950-1976; 1; 0.4 Cubic Feet 1 document case
  Scope and Contents
  This series contains personal correspondence between Loucks and people associated with the China Medical Board. It includes some administrative correspondence regarding the Peking Union Medical College.
  Of special interest in the Correspondence series is the Reinhard Hoeppli file of letters, which describe in some detail the "PUMC" and China after 1951.
  - Bowers, John Z., 1969-1972 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Cort, Nellie G. and William W., 1967 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Curran, Jean Alonzo, 1969-1975 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Danaraj, T. J., 1965-1969 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Dieuaide, Francis R., 1952, 1968-1975 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Dock, William, 1952 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Ferguson, Mary E., 1966-1975 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Gregg, Alan, 1952-1954 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Hastings, A. Baird, 1947 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Hoeppli, Reinhard, 1952-1954, 1966-1971 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Houghton, Henry S., 1952-1954, 1960-1972 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Ingram, Ruth, 1949-1960, 1965-1972 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Kilborn, Leslie G., 1965 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Lim, C. E., 1958-1959, 1962, 1972-1975 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - McClure, Robert B., 1971-1974 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - McFadzean, Alec J. S. and Florence, 1952-1954, 1964-1976 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Opie, Eugene L., 1968 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Parker, Philo W., 1947-1956, 1960, 1971 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Schultz, Edwin W., 1959 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Scouel, Frederick G., 1953-1957, 1967 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Taylor, Adrian S. and Annie May, 1920-1922, 1952-1954, 1961 (Box 1, Folder 21)
- China Medical Board, Inc., 1946-1964, bulk 1951-1964; 1951-1964; 2; 4 Cubic Feet 1 document case
  This series includes a report from a Rockefeller Foundation sponsored commission in regard to medical education in China in 1946 and reports from the Future Program Committee of the China Medical Board, Inc. (1951-1955). Most of the box covers trips Loucks made to the Far East (1951-1964) to investigate medical education there.
  - Rockefeller Foundation - China Commission, 1946 (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - Planning Committee, 1951-1955 (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - War Claims Act, circa 1962 (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - Trip, 1951 (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - Trip, 1953 (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - Trip, 1955 (Box 2, Folder 27)
  - Trip, 1958 (Box 2, Folder 28)
  - Trip, 1959 (Box 2, Folder 29)
  - Trip, 1960-1961 (Box 2, Folder 30)
  - Trip, 1964-1965 (Box 2, Folder 32)
- China Medical Board - Peking Union Medical College, 3; 4 Cubic Feet 1 document case
  This series consists of the manuscript for the book "China Medical Board - Peking Union Medical College," (New York, 1970) which Loucks collaborated on with the author, Mary E. Ferguson. Included are a condensation and the original length manuscript, as well as reviews of the book. Also in this box are reprints of articles by Paul C. Hodges.
  - Introduction, Chapters 1-4 (Box 3, Folder 33)
  - Chapters 5-8 (Box 3, Folder 34)
  - Chapters 9-11 (Box 3, Folder 35)
  - Chapters 12-14 (Box 3, Folder 36)
  - Chapters 15-16 (Box 3, Folder 37)
  - Chapters 17-18 (Box 3, Folder 38)
  - Chapters 19-20 (Box 3, Folder 39)
  - Chapters 21-23 (Box 3, Folder 40)
  - Chapters 24-26 (Box 3, Folder 41)
  - Chapter 27 (Box 3, Folder 42)
  - Condensed p. 1-57 (Box 3, Folder 43)
  - Condensed p. 58-144 (Box 3, Folder 44)
  - Condensed p. 145-207 (Box 3, Folder 45)
  - Condensed p. 208-272 (Box 3, Folder 46)
  - Correspondence/Reviews (Box 3, Folder 47)
  - Articles - Hodges, Paul C. (Box 3, Folder 48)